<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<entry xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>http://tobyinkster.co.uk/blog/2003/08/31/chilli/</id>
  <link rel="self" href="http://tobyinkster.co.uk/blog/2003/08/31/chilli/"/>
  <title>Chilli con Carne</title>
  <author>
    <name>Toby Inkster</name>
    <email>mail@tobyinkster.co.uk</email>
    <uri>http://tobyinkster.co.uk/</uri>
  </author>
  <content type="text/html" mode="xml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><h2>Ingredients<br/>
 <br/>
* 2, 3 or 4 (depending on how hot you like it!) chilli peppers, deseeded and chopped<br/>
* 500g minced beef<br/>
* 450g tin of chopped tomatos<br/>
* 450g tin of red kidney beans or mixed beans, drained<br/>
* 1 green pepper, chopped<br/>
* 1 medium onion, chopped<br/>
* 1 or 2 sticks of celery, chopped (optional)<br/>
* small handful of coursely chopped corriander<br/>
* Mexican spices<br/>
* gravy powder or cornflour<br/>
* oil</h2>

<h3>Spice Blend</h3>

<p>OK -- I have decided to reveal my tried-and-tested cajan/mexican spice blend exclusively on my website. You might want to make a big batch of this blend in advance. The quantities shown below will make too much spice blend for a normal sized batch of chilli!</p>

<p>Level one spices -- use about three teaspoons of each:</p>

<ul>
<li>cumin (seeds, toasted and roughly crushed; or powder)</li>
<li>chilli (dried flakes, or powder)</li>
<li>oregano (dried)</li>
</ul>

<p>Level two spices -- include about two teaspoons of each of these if you have them:</p>

<ul>
<li>corriander (crushed seeds and/or dried leaves)</li>
<li>garlic (dried powder, or crushed)</li>
<li>ginger (dried powder, or crushed)</li>
<li>unsweetended cocoa powder</li>
</ul>

<p>Level three spices -- include about one teaspoon of each of these if you have them:</p>

<ul>
<li>ground allspice</li>
<li>mustard seeds (dried)</li>
<li>black pepper</li>
<li>salt</li>
<li>parsley (dried)</li>
</ul>

<p>Bash those all together roughly in a pestle and mortar to create the spice blend.</p>

<p>If you are using any non-dry ingredients, to increase the shelf-life of the blend add plenty of sunflower oil and refridgerate. It should keep a couple of weeks.<br/>
 <br/>
h1. Method</p>

<p>Fry the chilli, onion, capsicum, celery and spices until the onion is transparent. Add beef and cook until brown, stirring occasionally. Add the kidney beans and tomatos. Simmer for 5 to 10 minutes. Thicken with gravy powder and simmer for a further 5 to 10 minutes.</p>

<p>Serve with rice and/or tortilla chips. Garnish with corriander leaves.</p></div>
  </content>
  <published>2003-08-31T13:11:10+01:00</published>
  <updated>2007-04-06T17:13:51+01:00</updated>
  <link rel="license" href="http://tobyinkster.co.uk/licence/c"/>
  <category term="spicy"/>
  <category term="mexico"/>
  <category term="chilli"/>
  <category term="beef"/>
  <category term="recipes"/>
  <category term="tomato"/>
</entry>
