<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<entry xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>http://tobyinkster.co.uk/blog/2008/03/28/saturday-nights/</id>
  <link rel="self" href="http://tobyinkster.co.uk/blog/2008/03/28/saturday-nights/"/>
  <title>Friday Evening: Saturday Nights &amp; Sunday Mornings</title>
  <author>
    <name>Toby Inkster</name>
    <email>mail@tobyinkster.co.uk</email>
    <uri>http://tobyinkster.co.uk/</uri>
  </author>
  <content type="text/html" mode="escaped">
&lt;div class="hreview"&gt;

  &lt;div class="description item haudio"&gt;
  
    &lt;a class="url" style="display:none" href="http://musicbrainz.org/release/8f918f54-09a6-4d8c-bb78-2a2aa9eca81c.htm"&gt;(MusicBrainz)&lt;/a&gt;
  
    &lt;p&gt;OK, so Amazon kindly delivered my copy of &lt;span class="summary"&gt;&lt;span class="contributor vcard"&gt;&lt;span class="fn org"&gt;Counting Crows&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;' &lt;i class="album album-title"&gt;Saturday Nights &amp;amp; Sunday Mornings&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/span&gt; this morning. I've made a point of not listening to any of the new songs that have been floating around the Internet, except &lt;i class="song-title"&gt;Cowboys&lt;/i&gt; which &lt;a rel="acquaintance" href="http://annabegins.com"&gt;Lisa&lt;/a&gt; sent to me ages ago. I waited until I finished work this afternoon and am currently listening to the album&amp;nbsp;&amp;#8212; I thought I owed it to the boys to listen the whole work so I can judge it as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Firstly I agree with what's been said on &lt;a href="news:alt.music.counting-crows"&gt;the newsgroup&lt;/a&gt; that this definitely feels like it could be a last ever album. It's got very much of a retrospective feel to it.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p class="item"&gt;As if to illustrate that, &lt;i class="song-title title"&gt;1492&lt;/i&gt; was of course an off-cut from their previous album. I've never been quite sure why they cut it&amp;nbsp;&amp;#8212; it was a great song, and would have fit in very nicely with the overall feel of &lt;span class="haudio"&gt;&lt;i class="album-title album"&gt;Hard Candy&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/span&gt;. It's still a great song though, and I'm glad it's finally seen the light of day.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p class="item"&gt;&lt;i class="song-title title"&gt;Hanging Tree&lt;/i&gt; has lovely production. The Crows' lyrics are never happy, but this song manages to have an uplifting sound to it, and is reminiscent of &lt;span class="haudio"&gt;&lt;i class="song-title title"&gt;Accidentally in Love&lt;/i&gt; from the &lt;span class="album"&gt;&lt;i class="film-title"&gt;Shrek 2&lt;/i&gt; soundtrack&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p class="item"&gt;&lt;i class="song-title title"&gt;Los Angeles&lt;/i&gt; is another old &lt;span class="haudio"&gt;&lt;i class="album album-title"&gt;Hard Candy&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/span&gt; reject. It would never have worked on that album, so I'm again happy that a place has been found for it. Co-written by Ryan Adams and The Gigolo Aunts' Dave Gibbs, the song has an anthemic, sing-along feel to it. It evokes many of Adam's lyrical motifs: the pressure of fame, American cities (especially San Francisco) and sleep.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p class="item"&gt;Rescued from the cutting room floor of the &lt;span class="haudio"&gt;&lt;i class="album-title album"&gt;Recovering the Satellites&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/span&gt; studio floor was &lt;i class="song-title title"&gt;Sundays&lt;/i&gt;. OK, so it was re-recorded for this album really. And given a &lt;span class="haudio"&gt;&lt;i class="song-title title"&gt;New Frontier&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/span&gt;-style intro. It's a solid song. Though perhaps it doesn't seem to quite gel with the rest of the &lt;i class="album-part"&gt;Saturday Nights&lt;/i&gt; songs, which have more of a rocky feel, it would be even more out of place on &lt;i class="album-part"&gt;Sunday Mornings&lt;/i&gt;, despite the name.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p class="item"&gt;&lt;i class="song-title title"&gt;Insignificant&lt;/i&gt; starts off as an average-to-middling-quality song, but has a wonderful, flowing guitar solo. Parts of it seem to have an underlying George Harrison-style Indian-influenced texture.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p class="item"&gt;&lt;i class="song-title title"&gt;Cowboys&lt;/i&gt; is a song of great contrasts: sparse choruses followed by rich instrumentals. It's one of the examples of self-reference on this album, including the line "anyone but you" in its chorus which is used as a track title on the second half of the album. Lots of Duritz' standard lyrical themes come up, including satellites, sleep, cowboys (of course) and mentions of "Saturday" and "Sunday", which seems to be a new motif especially for this album.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p class="item"&gt;Another fairly old unreleased song, first heard on their 2003 tour is &lt;i class="song-title title"&gt;Washington Square&lt;/i&gt;, the beginning of the more laid-back &lt;i class="album-part"&gt;Sunday Mornings&lt;/i&gt; part of the album. Wonderful harmonica and piano from Charlie Gillingham in this. The title evokes the lyrics of &lt;span class="haudio"&gt;&lt;i class="song-title title"&gt;August and Everything After&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/span&gt;, the song whose words are scrawled on the front of the band's first album while being strangely absent from its track listing.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p class="item"&gt;&lt;i class="song-title title"&gt;On Almost Any Sunday Morning&lt;/i&gt; name checks "Sunday" again, and "grey" (of course &lt;a class="url" href="http://www.lyricsdepot.com/counting-crows/mr-jones.html"&gt;Adam's favourite colour&lt;/a&gt;), continuing the self-referential theme of the album. Lots of superb harmonica again.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p class="item"&gt;&lt;i class="song-title title"&gt;When I Dream of Michelangelo&lt;/i&gt; seems like it's almost Adam's attempt to rethink &lt;span class="haudio"&gt;&lt;i class="song-title title"&gt;Angels of the Silences&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/span&gt; as a beautiful ballad. And it works well. From &lt;i class="song-title" title="Angels of the Silences"&gt;Angels&lt;/i&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I dream of Michelangelo when I'm lying in my bed&lt;br /&gt;
      Little angels hang above my head and read me like an open book&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;And from &lt;i class="song-title" title="When I Dream of Michelangelo"&gt;Michelangelo&lt;/i&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;And I dream of Michelangelo when I'm lying in my bed&lt;br /&gt;
      I see God upon the ceiling, I see angels overhead&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;

    &lt;p class="item"&gt;Another song that seems to have a Beatles-influenced sound is &lt;i class="song-title title"&gt;Anyone But You&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p class="item"&gt;&lt;i class="song-title title"&gt;You Can't Count on Me&lt;/i&gt; is a stand-out track on this part of this album. It's strongly melody-driven. If it wasn't for the uninspiring (note: "uninspiring", not "uninspired"!) lyrics it would make perfect film soundtrack fodder.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p class="item"&gt;&lt;i class="song-title title"&gt;Le Ballet D'Or&lt;/i&gt; begins very cut-back instrumentally, but as the song progresses, we see the sound becoming richer. Although it works well, part of me would like to hear what it would sound like as a simple &lt;span class="haudio"&gt;&lt;i class="song-title title"&gt;Walkaways&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/span&gt;-style acoustic guitar plus vocals track.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p class="item"&gt;It's almost a rule that every Crows album has a single piano-driven ballad. &lt;i class="song-title title"&gt;On a Tuesday in Amsterdam Long Ago&lt;/i&gt; is that track.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p class="item"&gt;&lt;i class="song-title title"&gt;Come Around&lt;/i&gt; was written and performed live during the 2003 &lt;span class="haudio"&gt;&lt;i class="album-title album"&gt;Hard Candy&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/span&gt; tour. Stylistically this song belongs as much to &lt;i class="album-part"&gt;Saturday Nights&lt;/i&gt; as it does to &lt;i class="album-part"&gt;Sunday Mornings&lt;/i&gt;; perhaps it's the beginning of a &lt;i class="album-part"&gt;Sunday Afternoons&lt;/i&gt; section. It's a nice way to finish the album off.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p class="item"&gt;Except that's not really the end of the album, is it? Continuing &lt;i class="album-part"&gt;Sunday Afternoons&lt;/i&gt; we have &lt;i class="song-title title"&gt;Baby I'm a Big Star Now&lt;/i&gt;, the song which is the subject of a bet Adam made many years ago. Somebody bet him he couldn't include the same song on four different releases and have me buy every one of them. This song is on the &lt;span class="haudio"&gt;&lt;i class="album-title album"&gt;This Desert Life&lt;/i&gt; LP&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="haudio"&gt;disc two of the &lt;i class="album-title album"&gt;Hanginaround&lt;/i&gt; EP&lt;/span&gt;, the &lt;span class="haudio"&gt;&lt;i class="album album-title"&gt;Films About Ghosts&lt;/i&gt; &lt;span class="description"&gt;best-of album&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; and now this album too. Despite that, I don't feel ripped off&amp;nbsp;&amp;#8212; if there was any song I had to buy four times, I would want it to be this one.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;The album as a whole has a handful of older tracks, and plenty of songs with lyrics which hark back to old favourites.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;It was interesting to see ex-&lt;abbr title="alt.music.counting-crows"&gt;a.m.c-c&lt;/abbr&gt; regular &lt;a href="http://groups.google.com/groups?as_ugroup=alt.music.counting-crows&amp;amp;as_uauthors=ehud+lazin&amp;amp;safe=off"&gt;Ehud Lazin&lt;/a&gt; thanked in the liner notes.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;span class="reviewer vcard" style="display:none"&gt;Reviewed by &lt;a class="url fn" rel="me" href="http://tobyinkster.co.uk/"&gt;Toby Inkster&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
  <published>2008-03-28T21:53:50Z</published>
  <updated>2008-03-29T23:01:38Z</updated>
  <link rel="license" href="http://tobyinkster.co.uk/licence/c"/>
  <category term="hreview"/>
  <category term="review"/>
  <category term="counting-crows"/>
  <category term="music"/>
</entry>
