<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<entry xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>http://tobyinkster.co.uk/blog/2008/11/30/wallander/</id>
  <link rel="self" href="http://tobyinkster.co.uk/blog/2008/11/30/wallander/"/>
  <title>Wallander</title>
  <author>
    <name>Toby Inkster</name>
    <email>mail@tobyinkster.co.uk</email>
    <uri>http://tobyinkster.co.uk/</uri>
  </author>
  <content type="text/html" mode="xml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>I meant to post this article a couple of weeks ago, but I've been very bad at updating my blog recently. The <span class="caps">BBC </span>is showing an adaptation of one of Henning Mankell's <em>Wallander</em> novels tonight. Mankell is one of my favourite crime fiction writers, so here are a few random thoughts (no spoilers!):</p>

<ul>
<li>They've started with <em>Sidetracked</em>, the fifth novel in the series. Probably a good choice -- it's the most critically acclaimed. The first in the series, <em>Faceless Killers</em>, is arguably the weakest Wallander novel so would not be a good choice if the production company is hoping to have a series commissioned.</li>
<li>Rather than try to compress the whole novel into a 90 minute show, the <span class="caps">BBC </span>has wisely made it into a mini-series. This is an excellant choice as it's quite a twisty, turny story, and needs a bit of time devoted to it.</li>
<li>Kenneth Brannagh will probably turn out to be an excellant choice of actor to play Kurt Wallander.</li>
<li>I wonder if they relocate the novels from Sweden to the UK? I hope not. But if not, I wonder how they deal with the fact that at certain points in many of the novels, Wallander is required to speak English, a language in which he is not particularly fluent. (Accents, a la <em>'Allo 'Allo</em>?)</li>
</ul>

<p>Anyway, I'll certainly be watching tonight!</p>

<p><strong>Update:</strong> So it seems that it <em>was</em> a whole novel in a 90 minute show. The next two episodes will be different novels. Obviously when you shoehorn quite a complex plot into an hour and a half, some things are left out, but I think the general gist of the story was caught well, and Mankell's atmospherics were captured beautifully.</p>

<p>Airing the fifth novel first also requires a little bit of creative continuity. For example, in this episode, Kurt Wallander and his wife have agreed to a trial separation, even though they had already divorced in the first novel. Overall, the adaptation was, I'd say, a success.</p></div>
  </content>
  <published>2008-11-30T19:41:07Z</published>
  <updated>2008-11-30T22:38:23Z</updated>
  <link rel="license" href="http://tobyinkster.co.uk/licence/c"/>
  <category term="wallander"/>
  <category term="bbc"/>
  <category term="sweden"/>
</entry>
