<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<entry xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>http://tobyinkster.co.uk/blog/2007/02/20/atheist-ethics/</id>
  <link rel="self" href="http://tobyinkster.co.uk/blog/2007/02/20/atheist-ethics/"/>
  <title>Re: A treatise on how religious Atheism is</title>
  <author>
    <name>Toby Inkster</name>
    <email>mail@tobyinkster.co.uk</email>
    <uri>http://tobyinkster.co.uk/</uri>
  </author>
  <content type="text/html" mode="escaped">&lt;p&gt;TomP wrote:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;[Atheists] do not believe in the existence of a soul.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although most Buddhists do not believe in any gods, and can therefore be described as atheists, they most certainly do believe in the concept of a soul -- indeed, a soul that can continue to exist after death.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;You do not believe in any source for ethical conduct except sources within human beings&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There have been several good ethical theories put forward that go further than "look within yourself and you&amp;#39;ll know what&amp;#39;s right". Arguably, the two that seem to gel best with current observed human ethics are Kantian ethics and Utilitarianism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kantian ethics look at the means rather than the ends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We ask, should one do X?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We imagine a world where everyone does X.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is this world flawed?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If so, one should never do X.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If not, one may do X.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is, if we want to know whether it is morally acceptable to lie, we imagine a world where everyone lied all the time. Nobody would be able to get anything done in such a world. (Imagine a trip to the shops: "that&amp;#39;ll be &amp;Atilde;&amp;#131;&amp;Acirc;&amp;#130;&amp;Atilde;&amp;#130;&amp;Acirc;&amp;pound;10.49", "really?", "no... actually it&amp;#39;s &amp;Atilde;&amp;#131;&amp;Acirc;&amp;#130;&amp;Atilde;&amp;#130;&amp;Acirc;&amp;pound;8.49", "ok, here&amp;#39;s &amp;Atilde;&amp;#131;&amp;Acirc;&amp;#130;&amp;Atilde;&amp;#130;&amp;Acirc;&amp;pound;10 -- keep the change", handing the shopkeeper a &amp;Atilde;&amp;#131;&amp;Acirc;&amp;#130;&amp;Atilde;&amp;#130;&amp;Acirc;&amp;pound;5 note.) And so Kantian ethics says that lying is wrong. It doesn&amp;#39;t consider the fact that some lies may make people happy. ("Love the haircut!")&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Utilitarianism is the philosophy that one should do what increases the world&amp;#39;s total level of happiness. So while, say, all murders might be deemed unethical under Kant, utilitarianism says that murder is &lt;span class="caps"&gt;OK, &lt;/span&gt;provided it increases the world&amp;#39;s total level of happiness, so it may well be that murdering an internationally reviled figure (e.g. Hitler) would be deemed ethically allowable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think that most people tend to sit somewhere between those two extremes. There are certain actions where they take a more Kantian viewpoint (e.g. murder is always wrong), and others where they take a more utilitarian view (e.g. it is OK to lie if it makes people happy and doesn&amp;#39;t harm anyone). One does "look within" to find ones own personal balance between these two ethical codes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But that&amp;#39;s not to say that tomorrow, or the next day, or some other time in the future, some bright philosopher will find a code of ethics that unifies Kantian and Utilitarian ethics in a non-personal and non-arbitrary way, and publish a code of ethics that everyone would be prepared to subscribe to.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
  <published>2007-02-20T17:49:56Z</published>
  <updated>2007-04-08T18:06:36+01:00</updated>
  <link rel="license" href="http://tobyinkster.co.uk/licence/mirror"/>
  <category term="soul"/>
  <category term="atheism"/>
  <category term="ethics"/>
</entry>
