<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<entry xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>http://tobyinkster.co.uk/blog/2008/03/29/earth-hour/</id>
  <link rel="self" href="http://tobyinkster.co.uk/blog/2008/03/29/earth-hour/"/>
  <title>Earth Hour</title>
  <author>
    <name>Toby Inkster</name>
    <email>mail@tobyinkster.co.uk</email>
    <uri>http://tobyinkster.co.uk/</uri>
  </author>
  <content type="text/html" mode="escaped">&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Sydney Morning Herald&lt;/em&gt; has just (about 2 hours ago) &lt;a href="http://www.smh.com.au/news/earth-hour/please-take-a-bow-sydney/2008/03/30/1206207512977.html?page=2"&gt;reported&lt;/a&gt; that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year, 26 cities joined Earth Hour as official partner cites, including -- along with all of Australia&amp;#39;s capitals -- Atlanta, Bangkok, Chicago, Christchurch, Copenhagen, Dublin, Manila, Montreal, Odense, Ottawa, Phoenix, San Francisco, Tel Aviv and Toronto.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;US, &lt;/span&gt;the lights were going out on San Francisco&amp;#39;s Golden Gate Bridge and Alcatraz Island, and Chicago&amp;#39;s Sears Tower. North of the border, Canada was turning off the lights at Toronto&amp;#39;s CN Tower and the floodlights at Niagara Falls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Britain, Brighton Pier was blacked out, and Prince Charles gave Earth Hour royal approval by turning off the lights at Highgrove House, his Gloucestershire home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I do appreciate that it&amp;#39;s very late in Sydney now, and the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SMH&lt;/span&gt;&amp;#39;s reporters want to be tucked up in bed at home, but that&amp;#39;s no excuse for such shoddy reporting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can vouch that Brighton Pier &lt;em&gt;was not&lt;/em&gt; blacked out. It may &lt;em&gt;well&lt;/em&gt; be in three and a half hours time when Earth Hour reaches &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GMT, &lt;/span&gt;but right now it&amp;#39;s still light outside, so there would be little point in having Earth Hour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lights on San Franscisco&amp;#39;s Golden Gate Bridge have probably gone out, yes, but that&amp;#39;s because the sun has just risen there -- it&amp;#39;s barely even breakfast time yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earth Hour does not have the environmental benefits that its proponents claim. Preliminary statistics from Sydney suggest roughly a 10% dip in electricity consumption during the hour. That&amp;#39;s an annual energy saving of 0.00114% -- barely even a blip. Caroline Overington&amp;#39;s &lt;a href="http://blogs.theaustralian.news.com.au/coverington/index.php/theaustralian/comments/earth_hour_is_a_turn_off/P75/"&gt;scathing blog entry&lt;/a&gt; has more such info.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That having been said, Earth Hour does raise awareness for what is a very important global issue. And it is for that reason that lights in the Inkster household will be dimmed at 8.00&amp;nbsp;pm.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
  <published>2008-03-29T16:31:30Z</published>
  <updated>2008-03-29T16:31:30Z</updated>
  <link rel="license" href="http://tobyinkster.co.uk/licence/c"/>
  <category term="shoddy-reporting"/>
  <category term="east-sussex"/>
  <category term="earth-hour"/>
  <category term="environment"/>
</entry>
