<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<entry xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>http://tobyinkster.co.uk/blog/2003/08/31/carbonara/</id>
  <link rel="self" href="http://tobyinkster.co.uk/blog/2003/08/31/carbonara/"/>
  <title>Spaghetti alla Carbonara</title>
  <author>
    <name>Toby Inkster</name>
    <email>mail@tobyinkster.co.uk</email>
    <uri>http://tobyinkster.co.uk/</uri>
  </author>
  <content type="text/html" mode="xml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>Traditionally, Carbonara sauce includes raw egg, but that of course
 carries with it a risk of salmonela infection. My recipe instead uses
 white sauce as a substitute.</p>
 
 <h2>Ingredients</h2>
 
 <ul>
<li>4 rashers of pancetta or smoked bacon</li>
<li>1 medium onion, chopped</li>
<li>2 to 3 cloves of garlic, finely chopped</li>
<li>1 1/2 teaspoons of dried chopped basil</li>
<li>1 1/2 teaspoons of dried chopped oregano</li>
<li>150g dried spaghetti</li>
<li>200 mL milk</li>
<li>30g butter</li>
<li>50g cheddar, grated</li>
<li>a little flour</li>
<li>pepper to taste</li>
<li>1 tablespoon mayonnaise (optional)</li>
 </ul>
 
 <h2>Method</h2>
 <p class="method">
 Grill the bacon until it starts to crisp. Then leave to cool. Once cool, chop
 into 1 cm wide strips.
 </p>
 
 <p class="method">
 Heat roughly 30g butter in a small saucepan. Add nearly all the milk (retaining
 about 50 mL) and bring almost to the boil. Mix the remaining cold milk with a little
 flour to form a smooth paste. Stir this paste into the hot milk. Stir in the cheese
 and mayonnaise. The sauce should now be fairly thick - if not, add more flour,
 sieving it and stirring continuously to avoid lumps in the sauce.</p>
 
 <p class="method">
 Fry the onions and garlic in the remaining butter until they start to become
 transparent. Put the fried onions, chopped bacon, basil, oregano and pepper into
 the white sauce and stir well.
 </p>
 
 <p class="method">
 Now prepare the spaghetti according to the instructions found on its packaging.
 Make sure you keep stirring the sauce occasionally.
 </p>
 
 <p class="method">
 Put the spaghetti into serving bowls and pour sauce over. Garnish with
 parmesan cheese and a sprig of fresh basil or oregano. If hungry, serve with
 garlic bread.
 </p>

</div>
  </content>
  <published>2003-08-31T13:29:40+01:00</published>
  <updated>2008-01-01T18:35:47Z</updated>
  <link rel="license" href="http://tobyinkster.co.uk/licence/c"/>
  <category term="pasta"/>
  <category term="bacon"/>
  <category term="recipes"/>
  <category term="italy"/>
</entry>
