<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<entry xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>http://tobyinkster.co.uk/blog/2004/11/13/united-welfare-states/</id>
  <link rel="self" href="http://tobyinkster.co.uk/blog/2004/11/13/united-welfare-states/"/>
  <title>The United (Welfare) States of America</title>
  <author>
    <name>Toby Inkster</name>
    <email>mail@tobyinkster.co.uk</email>
    <uri>http://tobyinkster.co.uk/</uri>
  </author>
  <content type="text/html" mode="xml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Red E. Kilowatt wrote:</p>

<blockquote><p>The endless flood of new people who are living at or below the poverty level make overwhelming demands on local public services. [...] We might as well put up a big neon sign at the border that says, "Come one, come all.</p></blockquote>

<p>You already have one. It says:</p>

<blockquote class="alt"><p>Give me your tired, your poor, <br/>
Your huddled masses yearning to breathe free, <br/>
The wretched refuse of your teeming shore. <br/>
Send these, the homeless, tempest-tossed to me. <br/>
I lift my lamp beside the golden door.</p></blockquote>

<blockquote><p>Free Healthcare. </p></blockquote>

<p>In a ranking<sup class="footnote"><a href="#fn1">1</a></sup> of Japan, Sweden, Canada, France, Australia, Spain, Finland, Netherlands, <span class="caps">UK,</span> Denmark, Belgium, <span class="caps">USA </span>and Germany, the <span class="caps">USA </span>was ranked:</p>

<ul>
<li>13th (last) for low-birth-weight percentages </li>
<li>13th for neonatal mortality and infant mortality overall </li>
<li>11th for postneonatal mortality </li>
<li>13th for years of potential life lost (excluding external causes) </li>
<li>11th for life expectancy at 1 year for females, 12th for males </li>
</ul>

<p>In the <span class="caps">USA </span>there are<sup class="footnote"><a href="#fn1">1</a></sup>:</p>

<ul>
<li>12,000 deaths/year from unnecessary surgery </li>
<li>7,000 deaths/year from medication errors in hospitals </li>
<li>20,000 deaths/year from other errors in hospitals</li>
<li>80,000 deaths/year from infections acquired in hospital</li>
</ul>

<p>That's healthcare in general... now on to the "free" stuff... (of course, it's not actually free, but paid for through taxes)</p>

<p>The US government only provides Medicare for about 15% of the population -- those that are 65 or older, younger people with disabilities and kidney failure.</p>

<p>Compared that with her neighbour Canada -- Canadian provinces are required<sup class="footnote"><a href="#fn2">2</a></sup> to provide all residents with free health care that covers almost all procedures. Patients can choose their own doctor, hospital, etc... 98% of hospital care in Canada is paid for by the state.</p>

<p>In Australia, the Medicare system does not provide completely free treatment, but instead vastly subsidises health care. The patient only has to pay 15% of the cost of his/her care, up to a maximum of about $50.00.</p>

<p>In the <span class="caps">UK, </span>the <span class="caps">NHS </span>covers most treatment for free. It is the third largest employer in the world, after the Chinese Army and Indian Railways.</p>

<p>Since South Africa adopted a comprehensive publically-funded healthcare scheme soon after the fall of apartheid, the <span class="caps">USA </span>has been virtually the only developed country not to have one!</p>

<blockquote><p>Free Education.</p></blockquote>

<p>American eighth-grade students performed:</p>

<ul>
<li>worse than Japanese and Canadian students at both mathematics and science<sup class="footnote"><a href="#fn3">3</a></sup>;</li>
<li>equal to Russian students in science, but worse in maths<sup class="footnote"><a href="#fn3">3</a></sup>;</li>
<li>equal to British students in maths, but worse in science<sup class="footnote"><a href="#fn4">4</a></sup>.</li>
</ul>

<p>In a <span class="caps">UNICEF </span>study of 24 industrialised countries<sup class="footnote"><a href="#fn5">5</a></sup>, counting the percentage of 15-year-olds falling behind international benchmarks, the <span class="caps">USA </span>came 7th highest (with high=bad, low=good). Worse than Canada, Britain, Sweden and France. It just beat Germany though. (However Germany has higher adult literacy levels.)</p>

<p>Yet the <span class="caps">USA </span>spends more money on education than most other developed countries<sup class="footnote"><a href="#fn6">6</a></sup>.</p>

<blockquote><p>Opportunities for advancement and eventual citizenship. All you have to do is wait till nightfall and sneak across the border. And if you're pregnant, have your baby here and he will be granted instant citizenship, entitling you to free room and board (welfare) and the right to stay in the <span class="caps">US.</span></p></blockquote>

<p>Citizenship to babies born within a country's borders is refered to as "jus soli". </p>

<p>Many countries, including most of Europe, extend jus soli<sup class="footnote"><a href="#fn7">7</a></sup> with very few strings attached. (One common exception is for the children of visiting diplomats.)</p>

<blockquote><p>How many European countries operate that way?</p></blockquote>

<p>Lots.</p>

<p>***</p>

<p class="footnote" id="fn1"><sup>1</sup> "Is US Health Really the Best in the World?", Barbara Starfield MD <span class="caps">MPH,</span> Journal of the American Medical Association (JAMA), 2000-07-26. (PMID: 10904513)</p>

<p class="footnote" id="fn2"><sup>2</sup> Canada Health Act</p>

<p class="footnote" id="fn3"><sup>3</sup> Third International Mathematics and Science Repeat Study, 1999.</p>

<p class="footnote" id="fn4"><sup>4</sup> I wonder why??<br/>
<a href="http://archives.cnn.com/2002/EDUCATION/09/26/creationism.evolution/">http://archives.cnn.com/2002/EDUCATION/09/26/creationism.evolution/</a></p>

<p class="footnote" id="fn5"><sup>5</sup> <a href="http://archives.cnn.com/2002/EDUCATION/11/26/education.rankings.reut/">http://archives.cnn.com/2002/EDUCATION/11/26/education.rankings.reut/</a></p>

<p class="footnote" id="fn6"><sup>6</sup> "Comparative Indicators of Education in the United States and Other G-8 Countries: 2002", Joel D. Sherman, Steven D. Honegger, Jennifer L. McGivern, March 2003.</p>

<p class="footnote" id="fn7"><sup>7</sup> Aside: one exception is Japan which only extends jus soli in cases where the nationality of a child's parents is unknown or they have no nationality. I was born in Tokyo, but am not a Japanese citizen.</p></div>
  </content>
  <published>2004-11-13T12:29:00Z</published>
  <updated>2007-04-08T20:13:14+01:00</updated>
  <link rel="license" href="http://tobyinkster.co.uk/licence/mirror"/>
  <category term="education"/>
  <category term="america"/>
  <category term="politics"/>
  <category term="nhs"/>
</entry>
